Guide to the Thomas M. Disch Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- June 1991 Acquisition, 1956-1991; 23.04; (25 boxes)
  - Writings, Series I
    - "An Instructional Sonnet for a Poet Thinking of Moving to New York," poem, typescript, undated
    - Interview by Crowley, typescript, with manuscript corrections and audiotape, undated
    - Interview by David Lehman, typescript, 1987
    - "Intolerance," poem, typescript, 1969 October 2
    - "Introduction," essay, typescript, undated
    - "Introduction: On the Language of Ribaldry," essay, typescript, undated
    - "An Introduction to Transcastism," series of poems, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Introductions," essay, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Invaded by Love," short story, typescript, 1966
    - "The Invasion of the Giant Stupid Dinosaurs," short story, published clipping, undated
    - "Inventory," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Invitation to the Dinner," poem, typescript, undated
    - "It Is the Thought That Counts," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Ivy League Suit," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Jahweh's Wife," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Jane Rose," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Jaws of Safety," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Jekyll and Hyde '71," screenplay, typescript, photostat, undated
    - "Jellied Eel," poem, typescript, undated
    - "John Updike Writing a Story for the New Yorker," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Jocelin Schrager Story" (short story)
      - Fictional introduction, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Typescript, undated
    - "Joyful Feelings," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Just Friends #3," collected poems by various authors, typescript, 1970
    - "Koch on Broadway," short script, typescript, undated
    - "The Language of Ribaldry," article, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "A Largeness Unrelaxed," poem, typescript, 3 copies, 1969 October 16
    - "A Lasting Happiness," prose fragment, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Lazarus Maundering," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Leader of the Revolution," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Learning to Cross the Street," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Left Right Left Right," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Let Us Quickly Hasten to Gates of Ivory," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Life Sentences," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Likeness of Cognates," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Linda and Daniel and Spike," short story, typescript, and published clipping, undated
    - "Linda Lee," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Lines on the Job," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Listening to the News," poem, typescript, undated
    - Lists of poems, catalogues of Disch poems, typescript, with autograph notes, undated
    - "Little Poems," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Liver Goes," poem, typescript, 4 copies, 1968 January 25
    - "The Long Poem," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 3 copies, 1 signed, undated
    - "Loss of Short-Term Memory," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Lost in the Cosmos," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Love," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Love and Clover: A White Paper," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Luxe, Calme, et Desespoir," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Lyric," poem, typescript, undated
    - The M. D. (novel)
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, 1990; 6
      - Notes for a novel, typescript and manuscript, 1989
      - Book Five, cancelled draft, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1990; 2 (Box 8)
      - Proofs, with manuscript corrections, 1990; 5
      - Revised proofs, 1990; 5
      - Proofs, master set, with manuscript corrections, 1990; 5
      - Typescript, with manuscript notes, 1990; 7
      - Notes for a novel, typescript, manuscript, and clippings, 1989
      - Novel fragments, typescript and manuscript, 1990
      - Novel fragments, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1990; 3 (Box 9)
    - "The Mad Governess," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 3 copies, undated
    - "The Major Romantic Poets," poem, typescript, photocopy, undated
    - The Man Who Had No Idea (short story collection)
      - Introduction, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Typescript, carbon, undated
      - Typescript, undated
      - Short story, typescript, undated
    - "The Mandarin" (poem)
      - Typescript, carbon, undated
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - Mankind Under The Leash, novel, typescript, with manuscript corrections, undated
    - "The Marching Song of the Slum Landlords," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Marching Raspberries," short story, typescript, undated
    - "For Marilyn Hacker," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Martian jelly beans are fuzzy," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Master of the Milford Altarpiece," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Master Said-And-Done," short story, typescript, undated
    - "MCMLXXXIV," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "Memento Mori," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Memo," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Metamorphosis II," short story, typescript, with autograph notes and photocopied clippings, undated
    - "Milton on Fifth Avenue," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "Mindblowers," proposal for an anthology, typescript, undated
    - "Mini-list," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Minnesota Gothic," short story, published clipping, undated
    - "The Mittens of Ulysses," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 4 copies, undated
    - "A Model Prison," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1981
    - "Moondust, the Smell of Hay, and Dialectical Materialism," short story, typescript, and published clipping, undated
    - "A Movie at Academy One," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Museum of Modern Art," poem, typescript, undated
    - "My Flat," poem, typescript, water damage, undated
    - "My Mother: A Discussion," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "My Willoughby Personality Schedule," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Myron I," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Mystery Diet of the Gods," short story, typescript, undated
    - "NADA," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, and published clipping, undated
    - "NBCC Award Presentation," introduction, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "Narcissus and Echo," poem, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "Natural Science," poem, typescript, undated
    - Neighbors (novel)
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, undated; 4
      - Proofs, undated; 2
    - Neighboring Lives (novel)
      - Typescript, 1981; 2
      - Typescript, 1981; 2 (Box 10)
    - New Constellations (anthology)
      - Introduction and table of contents, typescript, carbon, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Reviews by various authors, typescript, photocopies and clippings, 1976
      - Contracts and financial records, 1974-1979
    - "The New Fashions," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "The New Godiva," essay, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "The New Grub Street Sonnets," poem, 2 copies, undated
    - The New Improved Sun (anthology)
      - Introductions, contents, and story clipping, typescript, carbon, undated
      - Reviews by various authors, typescript, photocopies and clippings, 1975
      - Contracts and financial records, 1973-80
    - "The New Man," short story, autograph manuscript, undated
    - "The News, Considered As a Romantic Fiction," essay, typescript, undated
    - "Nostalgia," short story, published clipping, undated
    - Notebooks, autograph manuscript, spiral-bound, card covers, undated; 11
    - Notes and clippings, miscellaneous items, 1958-1976, undated
    - "The Novel: A Sonnet," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1976 August 8
    - "Now Is Forever," short story, typescript and published clipping, undated
    - "The Number You Have Reached," short story, typescript, and published clipping, 3 copies, undated
    - "Nyctomene," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Ocean Interfaces," research project, typescript, 1981
    - "Ogden Nash," essay, typescript and manuscript notes, undated
    - "On Depositing the Check for a Legacy," poem, typescript, undated
    - "On the Use of the Masculine-Preferred," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - On Wings of Song (novel)
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Bound proof, with manuscript corrections, 1979
    - "1-A," short story, typescript, and published clipping, undated
    - "102 H-Bombs," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Opening the Heart: A Guide to Prosody," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - Orders of the Retina (poetry collection)
      - Typescript, undated
      - Typescript, undated
    - "Orientating Mr. Blank," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Our Novel," essay, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Painting," series of poems, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1980 January
    - "Palindrome," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated; 2
    - "The Pentagon," poem, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "Pentheus," poem, typescript, 1969 March 12
    - "The People Who Worked," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Perfect Strangers," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Perilous Cargo," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Persistence of Desire," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Perspectives," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Peter Schjeldahl," poem, typescript, undated (Box 11)
    - "Pishogues for the '80's," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Planet of the Rapes," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "A Plea That the Spring Might Return," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "A Poem Advertising John Sladek," poem, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "Poem of Turnip," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Poems from Plumbing," list of titles, autograph manuscript, undated
    - "Poisoned Apples," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Politics of Darkness," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Polonius at Delphi," essay, typescript, undated
    - "Portrait of a Tourist," poem, typescript, 5 copies, undated
    - "Post Mortem," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 3 copies, undated
    - "Praise," poem, typescript, undated
    - "A Prayer for the Harvest," poem, typescript, 4 copies, undated
    - "Prayer to the Virgin," poem, typescript, undated
    - The Pressure of Time (novel)
      - Synopsis and Book I, undated
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Typescript, with autograph corrections, undated; 2
      - Book II, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated; 2
      - Book II, typescript, carbon, undated
      - Novel fragment, typescript, photocopy, undated
      - Fragments, typescript and autograph notes, undated
    - "Priestess of Urania," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Princess Carillon," short story, typescript, undated
    - The Prisoner (novel)
      - Typescript, with manuscript corrections, undated; 3
      - Typescript, photostat, undated; 3
    - "The Prisoners of War," poem, typescript, undated
    - "A Prize Poem," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Product is God," notes for a novel, typescript and manuscript, undated
    - Publications, miscellaneous references to Thomas Disch, 1968-1970
    - "A Pumpkin for Claude Lorrain," poem, typescript, 4 copies, undated
    - "A Pumpkin for Richard Eberhart," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Pursuer," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Pyramids for Minnesota," essay, photocopy of published version, undated
    - "Representation in SF," transcript of lecture, typescript, 1971
    - "Reredos," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Return of the Medusae," short story, typescript, undated
    - "The Return to Nature," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - Reviews
      - Ackerman's Gosh! Wow!; Cunningham's The Abyss; Rucker's Spacetime Donuts; Wolfe's The Sword of the Lictor, 2 drafts, typescript, with autograph corrections, and photocopy of published article, 1982 May
      - Appleton's Tom Swift novels, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Arden's Vox Pop, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Baird's Walk Out A Brother; Cormier's The Bumblebee Flies Anyway; Yep's Liar, Liar; typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Baker's Nightchild; Bishop's One Winter in Eden; Pekar's American Splendor; Powers' The Anubis Gates; Schodt's Manga! Manga!, 2 drafts, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1984 July
      - Barthelme's Sixty Stories; Bilker's Writing Science Fiction That Sells; Bleiler's Science Fiction Writers; Carroll's Alice's Adventures in Wonderland; Clarkson and Cross's World Folktales; Davidson's Collected Fantasies; Ernst's A Little Girl Dreams of Taking the Veil; Morice's Poetry Comics and A Visit from St. Alphabet; Singer's Collected Stories, 2 drafts, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Batchelor's The Birth of the People's Republic of Antarctica; Spinrad's The Void Captain's Tale; Wolfe's The Citadel of the Autarch, 2 drafts, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Baxter's The Impending Gleam; Goulart's Upside Downside; Haiblum's The Tsaddik of the Seven Wonders; Morice's Poetry Comics; Rucker's Software; Sladek's Roderick, 1 draft, typescript, with autograph corrections and photocopy of published article, 1982 July
      - Berman's All That Is Solid Melts Into Air, typescript, with autograph notes and corrections, undated
      - Berry's Let's Talk About series; Child's Dark Company; Falkner's The Last Stradivarius; Loughran's Dearest; Maclean's The Watcher; Martorell and de Galba's Tirant Lo Blanc; Rogers' The Adventures of Samurai Cat; Sheffield's Man on Earth, typescript, 1985 January
      - Bishop's No Enemy But Time; Jennings' Aztec; Rucker's Spacetime Donuts; White's The Maharajah and Other Stories, 1 draft, typescript and photocopy of published article, 1982 June
      - Bleiler's The Guide to Supernatural Fiction; Chalker's Medusa: A Tiger By the Tale; Donaldson's White Gold Wielder; Godfrey's Scientists Confront Creationism; Platt's DreamMakers, typescript, undated
      - Borges: A Reader, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - The Boy Who Followed Ripley, no author named, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Bradley's The Mists of Avalon; Brooks' The Elfstones of Shannara; Card's Hart's Hope; Roberts' King of the Wood; Salmonson's Heroic Visions; Straub's The Floating Dragon; Wagner's In a Lonely Place, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Brandon's The Spiritualists; Brook's The Oxford Book of Dreams; Dahl's Book of Ghost Stories; King's Pet Sematary; Opie's The Oxford Book of Narrative Verse; Sullivan's Lost Souls, typescript, 2 copies, 1984 May
      - Brodsky's poetry; Enzenberger's The Sinking of the Titanic, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Carr's Fantasy Annual V; Carroll's Voice of Our Shadow; Eulo's The Deathstone; King's Different Seasons; Saha's The Year's Best Fantasy Stories #8; Tracy's The Gothic Novel (1790- 1830); Wagner's The Year's Best Horror Stories: Series X, 2 drafts, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Crowley's Little, Big, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Dick's works (Philip K. Dick), typescript, 1984 November
      - Dick's The Transmigration of Timothy Archer, Valis, and The Divine Invasion; Heinlein's Friday, typescript, and photocopy of published article, 1982 September
      - Dick's Valis; Linney's Jesus Tales; Merrill's Scripts for the Pageant; Malzberg's Their Immortal Hearts; Rucker's White Light, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Eco's The Name of the Rose; Ellin's The Dark Fantastic; Hoban's Pilgermann; Lish's Dear Mr. Capote, typescript, with manuscript corrections, 2 copies, undated
      - Ellin's short stories, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Fraser's Mr. American; typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Gardner's Mickelsson's Son, Hubbard's Battlefield Earth, Shirley's Cellars, Yurrick's Richard A., typescript, with autograph corrections, 1982 November
      - Ginzburg's The Night Battles; Russ's How to Suppress Women's Writing; Updike's The Witches of Eastwick, 2 drafts, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Goldman's Control; Lortz's Lovers Living, Lovers Dead; Schell's The Fate of the Earth; Sheffield and Bischoff's The Selkie; Wooley and Wolfe's Old Fears, 3 drafts, typescript, with autograph corrections, and 2 published clippings, undated
      - Grant's The Dodd, Mead Gallery of Horror; Kafka's The Complete Stories; Tevis's The Queen's Gambit, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
      - Holmes' Shelley: the Pursuit, typescript, 1975
      - Huxley's Brave New World, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated (Box 12)
      - Jacob's Juror, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Jenning's Aztec, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Koch's Selected Poems, galley, 1985 April
      - Macauley's The Towers of Trebizond, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - McWilliam's A Little Stranger, typescript, undated
      - Raine's poetry, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Read's A Married Man, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Sladek's The Reproductive System, fragment, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Sue's The Wandering Jew; typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Tyler's novel, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Vidal's The Second American Revolution, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Rilke," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Ring," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Roaches," short story, typescript, and published clipping, undated
    - "Rocky Mountain Ramble," poem, typescript, 1985 August 20
    - The Ruins of Earth (short story collection)
      - Typescript, with manuscript notes, 1971; 3
      - Typescript, with manuscript notes, 1971; 3
      - Proposal for an anthology, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
      - Reviews by various authors, typescript, photocopies and clippings, 1972
      - Contracts and financial records, 1970-1980
    - "A Sacred Tableau," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Saturday March 14," poem, typescript, undated
    - School notebook, spiral-bound book with autograph notes, undated
    - "Science Fiction," essay, typescript, photostat, undated
    - "Science Fiction," outline for slide presentation, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Science Fiction: the State of the Art Today," essay, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Science Fiction Versus Literature," essay, typescript, with autograph corrections, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Sea Change," poem, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "The Seasons," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Second Coming," notes and outline for a novel, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Secret Legend," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Selecting a Tie," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Semaphore," short story, typescript, undated
    - "Sensation/Happiness/Solitude," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "Sestina," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Seven Ages of Woman," poem, typescript, with manuscript notes, undated
    - "Sharing An Experience," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Sheep," short passage, typescript, undated
    - "The Shirt's Tale," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "The Shore of Acid Lake," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Shrink," play fragment, typescript, undated
    - "The Sightseers," short story, typescript, undated
    - "The Silkworm Song," poem, typescript, 4 copies, undated
    - "The Silver Pillow," short story, typescript, undated
    - Singularities (short story collection)
      - Typescript, with related correspondence, 1982
      - Review, by Elizabeth Lynn, photocopy of printed version, 1983 March 13
    - "Six French Mattresses," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The 16th of October, 1966," poem, typescript, 1966 October 16
    - "Skydiver," poem, typescript, with manuscript notes, 3 copies, undated
    - "Slaves," short story, typescript, 1965
    - "So Grows the Tree," poem, typescript, with manuscript notes, undated
    - "Social Forms and Social Controls in the United States," term paper, typescript, with autograph notes, and published clipping, undated
    - "Solar Lottery," essay on the novel by Philip K. Dick, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Somethin'," poem, typescript, undated
    - "A Song for the Torture," poem, typescript, undated
    - "A Sonnet Translated From the Polish," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Sous les bras de Westbrookville," poem, typescript, with autograph corrections, 1983 July 16
    - "Souvenirs," short story, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "Speculum," anthology proposal, typescript, undated
    - "Spontaneous Combustion," poem, typescript, 3 copies, undated
    - "Springtime in Tokyo," and "Travelling Backwards," poems, typescript, undated
    - "The Squirrel Cage"
      - Libretto and accompanying letter, typescript, 1985 February 28
      - Libretto, typescript, 1985
      - Short story, typescript, and published clipping, undated
    - "Stage to Screen to VCR," video series review, typescript, undated
    - "The Sticking Point," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Strangeness," short story collection, typescript, with manuscript notes and published clippings, undated; 4
    - "Sun and Sea," poem, typescript, undated (Box 13)
    - "The Surprise," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Suspension of Disbelief," essay, typescript, with copy-editor's corrections and accompanying letter, 1985 March 19
    - "Sweetly Sings the Chocolate Budgie," short story, typescript, with autograph corrections, undated
    - "Symbols of Love and Death," poem, typescript, undated
    - "A Talk With Jean-Ann On Her First Visit to the Farm," poem, typescript, undated
    - "The Talking Head," notes for a novel, typescript, undated
    - "Tars," poem by Disch and Naylor, typescript, undated
    - "Teddy Bear's Tragedy," Chapter One, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Telephone," poem, typescript, 2 copies, undated
    - "The Tenderness," poem, typescript, undated
    - "Testosterone," poem, typescript, undated
    - Theater reviews
      - 5 plays in London: La Puta Vida Trilogy; The Seagull; Elektra; The Milk Train Doesn't Stop Here Anymore; Serious Money, typescript, galley, 1988 January 5
      - La Tragicomedia de Calisto y Melibea; Las Bachantes; The Bacchae, typescript, draft and galley, undated
      - Lady, Be Good!; Dreamgirls; An Evening With the President; Two Gentlemen of Verona, typescript, galley, 1987 August 3
      - Mary Tudor; 5 operas, typescript, draft, and galley, 1988 November 1